In the clustering problem we are
クラスタリングの問題では、
given an unlabeled data
ラベル付けされていないデータセットが渡されて、
set and we would like
アルゴリズムに自動で
to have an algorithm automatically
互いに密接なサブセット、または互いに密接なクラスタに
group the data into coherent
グループ分け
subsets or into coherent clusters for us.
して欲しい。
The K Means algorithm is by
K-Means アルゴリズムは
far the most popular, by
ずば抜けて人気のある、
far the most widely used clustering
ずば抜けて広く使われているクラスタリングアルゴリズムだ。
algorithm, and in this
このビデオでは、
video I would like to tell
K-Meansアルゴリズムとは何か、
you what the K Means Algorithm is and how it works.
それがどう機能するかを話していきたい。
The K means clustering algorithm is best illustrated in pictures.
K-Meansクラスタリングアルゴリズムは絵で表すのが一番。
Let's say I want to take
ここに見せたような
an unlabeled data set like
ラベルの無いデータセットが
the one shown here, and I
あるとしよう。
want to group the data into two clusters.
そしてこのデータを2つのクラスタにグループ分けしたい。
If I run the K Means clustering
K-Meansアルゴリズムを実行するとしたら
algorithm, here is what
これがやるべきことだ。
I'm going to do. The first step is to randomly initialize two
最初の一歩はランダムに2つの点を選ぶ、
points, called the cluster centroids.
これはクラスタの重心と呼ばれる。
So, these two crosses here,
そう、これら2つのバッテンが、
these are called the Cluster Centroids
クラスタ重心と呼ばれる物だ。
and I have two of them
そしてそれが2つなのは、
because I want to group my data into two clusters.
データを2つのクラスタにグループ分けしたいから。
K Means is an iterative algorithm and it does two things.
K-Meansはイテレーティブなアルゴリズムで、2つの事をする。
First is a cluster assignment
最初はクラスタの割り付けステップ。
step, and second is a move centroid step.
二番目は重心移動ステップ。
So, let me tell you what those things mean.
それらが何を意味するか解説していこう。
The first of the two steps in the
K-Meansのループの中の2つのステップの内、
loop of K means, is this cluster assignment step.
最初の方は、クラスタ割り付けのステップだ。
What that means is that, it's
その意味する所は
going through each of the
各手本を見ていって、
examples, each of these green
ここで示したのだと、この緑のドットを
dots shown here and depending
見ていき、
on whether it's closer to the
赤のクラスタ重心と青のクラスタ重心の
red cluster centroid or the
どちらと近いかによって、
blue cluster centroid, it is going
各データポイントを
to assign each of the
2つのクラスタのうちのどちらかに
data points to one of the two cluster centroids.
割り振る。
Specifically, what I mean
具体的にその意味する所を見ると、
by that, is to go through your
データセットを見ていって、
data set and color each
各点を赤か青に
of the points either red or
色付けしていく、
blue, depending on whether
赤のクラスタ重心に近いか
it is closer to the red
青のクラスタ重心に近いかに
cluster centroid or the blue
よって。
cluster centroid, and I've done that in this diagram here.
この図ではそれを実際にやってみた。
So, that was the cluster assignment step.
以上がクラスタ割り付けステップ。
The other part of K means, in the
K-Meansのループ内を
loop of K means, is the move
構成するもう一方は
centroid step, and what
重心の移動ステップだ。
we are going to do is, we
我らがやるべきことは、
are going to take the two cluster centroids,
2つのクラスタの重心を、
that is, the red cross and
つまり、赤のバッテンと
the blue cross, and we are
青のバッテンを、
going to move them to the average
同じ色で色付けされた点の平均へと
of the points colored the same colour.
移動する。
So what we are going
つまり我らがやる事は、
to do is look at all the
全ての赤の点を見て、
red points and compute the
平均を計算し、
average, really the mean
それは真に全ての赤い点の
of the location of all the red points,
平均だが、
and we are going to move the red cluster centroid there.
赤のクラスタの重心をそこへ移動する。
And the same things for the
同じ事を青のクラスタ重心にも
blue cluster centroid, look at all
行う。青い点を
the blue dots and compute their
全て見て、平均を計算し、
mean, and then move the blue cluster centroid there.
青のクラスタ重心をそこへ移動する。
So, let me do that now.
ではやってみよう。
We're going to move the cluster centroids as follows
クラスタ重心を以下のように動かし、
and I've now moved them to their new means.
それらは新しい平均へと移動した。
The red one moved like that
赤いのはこんな感じで動き、
and the blue one moved
青いのはこんな感じで動いた。
like that and the red one moved like that.
そして赤いのはこんな感じで動いた。
And then we go back to another cluster
そして次にあらたなクラスタ割り当てステップに戻る。
assignment step, so we're again
つまりまたラベルづけされていない
going to look at all of
手本を全て見ていって、
my unlabeled examples and depending
青と赤のどちらの重心に
on whether it's closer the red or the blue cluster centroid,
近いかによって、
I'm going to color them either red or blue.
それらを赤か青に色付けする。
I'm going to assign each point
各点に2つのクラスタ重心のどちらかを
to one of the two cluster centroids, so let me do that now.
割り振る、という事なので、やってみよう。
And so the colors of some of the points just changed.
幾つかの点の色は変わった。
And then I'm going to do another move centroid step.
そしてまた、重心移動のステップに進む。
So I'm going to compute the
つまり全ての青の点の
average of all the blue points,
平均を計算し、
compute the average of all
全ての赤の点の
cluster centroids like this, and
クラスタ重心をこんな感じで移動する。
so, let's do that again.
やってみよう。
Let me do one more cluster assignment step.
クラスタ割り振りステップをもう一回やってみよう。
So colour each point red
各点を赤か青に色分けする、
or blue, based on what it's
とちらに近いかに基づいて
closer to and then
そして次に
do another move centroid step and we're done.
重心移動のステップを行う。行った。
And in fact if you
そして実の所、
keep running additional iterations of
ここからさらにK-Meansのイテレーションを
K means from here the
走らせ続けても、
cluster centroids will not change
クラスタ重心はこれ以上
any further and the colours of
移動しない。そして点の色も
the points will not change any
これ以上は変わらない。
further. And so, this is
つまり、これが
the, at this point,
こここそが、K-Meansが
K means has converged and it's
収束する点だ。
done a pretty good job finding
そしてそれは、このデータの2つのクラスタを
the two clusters in this data.
探すには、かなり良い仕事をしている。
Let's write out the K means algorithm more formally.
ではK-Meansのアルゴリズムをよりフォーマルに記述しよう。
The K means algorithm takes two inputs.
K -Meansアルゴリズムは2つの入力を取る。
One is a parameter K,
一つ目はパラメータK、
which is the number of clusters
それはデータの中から見つけたい
you want to find in the data.
クラスタの数。
I'll later say how we might
あとでどうやってこのKを
go about trying to choose k, but
どうやって選んだらいいかの話をするつもりだが、
for now let's just say that
今のところはあるクラスタの数を
we've decided we want a
既に決めた、と
certain number of clusters and we're
しておこう。
going to tell the algorithm how many
そして幾つのクラスタがデータセットにあるかを
clusters we think there are in the data set.
アルゴリズムに伝えるとする。
And then K means also
そしてK-Meansはまた、
takes as input this sort
このようなラベルの無いトレーニングセットを
of unlabeled training set of
入力にとる。
just the Xs and
単なるxだけ。
because this is unsupervised learning, we
これは教師なし学習だから、
don't have the labels Y anymore.
もうラベルyは無い。
And for unsupervised learning of
そしてK-Meansの教師なし学習に対しては
the K means I'm going to
xiをRnのベクトルを
use the convention that XI
表すというコンベンションを
is an RN dimensional vector.
用いることにする。
And that's why my training examples
そんな訳でトレーニング手本はいまや、
are now N dimensional rather N plus one dimensional vectors.
n+1次元では無くn次元のベクトルとなる。
This is what the K means algorithm does.
これがK-Meansアルゴリズムがやる事だ:
The first step is that it
最初のステップは
randomly initializes k cluster
ランダムにK個の重心を選ぶ、
centroids which we will
それをミュー1、ミュー2、、、
call mu 1, mu 2, up
ミューkと名付ける
to mu k. And so
つまり、
in the earlier diagram, the
前の図だと、
cluster centroids corresponded to the
クラスタ重心は
location of the red cross
赤のバッテンと
and the location of the blue cross.
青のバッテンの場所に対応してた。
So there we had two cluster
つまりそれは、2つのクラスタ重心があったという事で、
centroids, so maybe the red
たとえば赤のバッテンが
cross was mu 1
ミュー1で、
and the blue cross was mu
青のバッテンがミュー2だった、という事。
2, and more generally we would have
そして今度はより一般的に
k cluster centroids rather than just 2.
2つだけじゃなくて、K個のクラスタ重心を考えていく。
Then the inner loop
するとK-Meansの内側のループは
of k means does the following,
以下を実行する、
we're going to repeatedly do the following.
つまり以下を繰り返し実行する事になる:
First for each of
まず、各トレーニング手本に対して
my training examples, I'm going
この変数c(i)を
to set this variable CI
xiに一番近いクラスタ重心のインデックスを
to be the index 1 through
セットする。
K of the cluster centroid closest to XI.
値は重心のインデックスである、1からKまでの値。
So this was my cluster assignment
つまりこれは、クラスタ割り付けステップにあたる。
step, where we
そこでは各サンプルに対して
took each of my examples and
それを赤か青か、
coloured it either red
そのどちらの重心に近いかに基づいて
or blue, depending on which
色分けしていく。
So CI is going to be
つまりc(i)は
a number from 1 to
1からKまでの数で、
K that tells us, you
その値は我らに
know, is it closer to the
それが赤のバッテンか
red cross or is it
青のバッテンか、
closer to the blue cross,
どちらに近いかを教えてくれる。
and another way of writing this
これの他の書き方としては、
is I'm going to,
ciを計算するのに、、、
to compute Ci, I'm
i番目の手本
going to take my Ith
xiを取ってきて
example Xi and and
それと個々の
I'm going to measure it's distance
クラスタ重心との
to each of my cluster centroids,
距離を測る。
this is mu and then
これがミューk、
lower-case k, right, so
小文字のk。
capital K is the total
大文字のKを重心の
number centroids and I'm going
総数を表すのに使い、
to use lower case k here
小文字のkを
to index into the different centroids.
重心を識別するインデックスに使う。
But so, Ci is going to, I'm going
そしてciを
to minimize over my values
kの値に関して最小化する、
of k and find the
そしてこのxiとクラスタ重心の
value of K that minimizes this
距離を最小化する
distance between Xi and the
kを探す。
cluster centroid, and then,
そして、
you know, the
あー、
value of k that minimizes
これを最小化する値kを、
this, that's what gets set in
そのkをciに代入する。
Ci. So, here's
以上がciとは何なのか？を
another way of writing out what Ci is.
記述するもう一つの書き方。
If I write the norm between
xi マイナス ミューk のノルム、
Xi minus Mu-k,
と書いた時は、
then this is the distance between
これはi番目のトレーニング手本と
my ith training example
クラスター重心の ミュー下付き添字k との
Xi and the cluster centroid
距離を表す。
Mu subscript K, this is--this
これ、この
here, that's a lowercase K. So uppercase
これは小文字のk。つまり大文字のKは
K is going to be
クラスタ重心の総数を
used to denote the total
表すのに
number of cluster centroids,
使う。
and this lowercase K's
そしてこの小文字のkは
a number between one and
1から大文字のKまでの間の数字で
capital K. I'm just using
異なるクラスタ重心同士を
lower case K to index
識別するのに
into my different cluster centroids.
小文字のkを使う。
Next is lower case k. So
それが小文字のk。
that's the distance between the example and the cluster centroid
これがサンプルとクラスタ重心の距離で、
and so what I'm going to
我らがやるべき事は
do is find the value
これを最小化する
of K, of lower case
k、このkは小文字のkだが、
k that minimizes this, and
それを探す。
so the value of
そしてその最小化するkの値を
k that minimizes you know,
ciに
that's what I'm going to
セットする。
set as Ci, and
そしてコンベンションにより、
by convention here I've written
xiとクラスタ重心の距離を
the distance between Xi and
実際には距離の二乗で
the cluster centroid, by convention
人々は
people actually tend to write this as the squared distance.
書いている。
So we think of Ci as picking
つまりciを、
the cluster centroid with the smallest
トレーニング手本xiとの二乗距離が
squared distance to my training example Xi.
最小になるクラスタ重心を選びとった物と考える事が出来る。
But of course minimizing squared distance,
だがもちろん、距離の二乗を最小化しようと、
and minimizing distance that should
距離を最小化しようと、
give you the same value of Ci,
同じciの値になるはず。
but we usually put in the
でも普通は二乗をつける。
square there, just as the
単なる慣例。
convention that people use for K means.
K-Meansを使う時の。
So that was the cluster assignment step.
以上がクラスタ割り付けステップ。
The other in the loop
K-Meansのループの中の
of K means does the move centroid step.
他の仕事は重心移動のステップだ。
And what that does is for
そこで行うのは、
each of my cluster centroids, so
クラスタ重心に対し、
for lower case k equals 1 through
つまり小文字のkを1から大文字のKまでの範囲で、
K, it sets Mu-k equals
ミューkにその重心に
to the average of the points assigned to cluster.
関連付けられた点たちの平均を代入する。
So as a concrete example, let's say
具体例としては、
that one of my cluster
クラスタ重心の一つ、
centroids, let's say cluster centroid
クラスタ重心2としよう、
two, has training examples,
それがトレーニング手本を持ってるとして、
you know, 1, 5, 6, and 10 assigned to it.
それは1、5、6、10に、それが割り振られているとする。
And what this means is,
その意味するところは、
really this means that C1 equals
c1=c5=c6=...
to C5 equals to
と、
C6 equals to and
c10も同様に
similarly well c10 equals, too, right?
イコールだ。
If we got that
クラスタ割り振りのステップで
from the cluster assignment step, then
それを得たとすると、
that means examples 1,5,6 and
それはつまり、手本1、5、6、10は
10 were assigned to the cluster centroid two.
クラスタ重心2が割り付けられている。
Then in this move centroid step,
次にこの重心移動のステップでは、
what I'm going to do is just
そこでやるべきは単に
compute the average of these four things.
これら4つの平均を取るという事。
So X1 plus X5 plus X6
つまりx1+x5+x6+x10と。
plus X10.
。
And now I'm going
そして今、それらを
to average them so here I
平均したいのだから、
have four points assigned to
このクラスタには点が4つ
this cluster centroid, just take
割り振られているのだから、
one quarter of that.
1/4を取る。
And now Mu2 is going to
するとミュー2は
be an n-dimensional vector.
n次元ベクトルとなる。
Because each of these
何故なら各手本、
example x1, x5, x6, x10
x1、x5、x6、x10は、
each of them were an n-dimensional
どれもn次元ベクトルだったから。
vector, and I'm going to
そしてこれらを
add up these things and, you
足し合わせて、
know, divide by four because I
4で割ってる、だって
have four points assigned to this
このクラスタ重心には
cluster centroid, I end up
4つの点が割り振られているから。
with my move centroid step,
その結果がクラスタ重心ミュー2の
for my cluster centroid mu-2.
重心移動のステップとなる。
This has the effect of moving
これはミュー2を
mu-2 to the average of
ここに列挙した4つの点の
the four points listed here.
平均となる。
One thing that I've asked is, well here we said, let's
よく質問される事として、今、
let mu-k be the average of the points assigned to the cluster.
ミューkをクラスタに割り振られた点の平均にしよう、と言ったが、
But what if there is
もし点を割り振られないクラスタ重心、
a cluster centroid no points
点が0個しか割り振られない
with zero points assigned to it.
クラスタ重心があったら、どうしたらいい？
In that case the more common
その場合、一番普通の対応は
thing to do is to just
たんにそのクラスタ重心を
eliminate that cluster centroid.
取り除く。
And if you do that, you end
そうすると、
up with K minus one clusters
最終結果はK個のクラスタではなくて
instead of k clusters.
K-1個のクラスタとなる。
Sometimes if you really need
時々、ほんとうにK個のクラスタが
k clusters, then the other
必要な場合もある。その場合にやる別の手段としては、
thing you can do if you
もし点が割り振られない
have a cluster centroid with no
クラスタ重心が
points assigned to it is you can
あったら、単にそのクラスタ重心を
just randomly reinitialize that cluster
ランダムに再初期化する。
centroid, but it's more
でも単に取り除く方が
common to just eliminate a
普通だね。
cluster if somewhere during
K-Meansの最中に
K means it with no points
クラスタ重心に
assigned to that cluster centroid, and
点が割り振られなかったら。
that can happen, altthough in practice
そしてそもそも実際には
it happens not that often.
そういう事はめったに起こらない。
So that's the K means Algorithm.
以上がK-Meansアルゴリズム。
Before wrapping up this video
このビデオのまとめに入る前に、
I just want to tell you
もう一つの良くある
about one other common application
K-Meansの応用を
of K Means and that's
話しておきたい。
to the problems with non well separated clusters.
それは、あまり綺麗に分かれていないクラスタの問題だ。
Here's what I mean.
それはこんな意味だ。
So far we've been picturing K Means
ここまではK-Meansを
and applying it to data
こんな感じのデータ、
sets like that shown here where
3つの綺麗に分かれたクラスタの
we have three pretty
データに対して
well separated clusters, and we'd
図解したり適用したりしてきた。
like an algorithm to find maybe the 3 clusters for us.
そしてアルゴリズムに3つのクラスタを探させてきた。
But it turns out that
だがK-Meansは
very often K Means is also
こんな感じのデータセットに対しても
applied to data sets that
とても良く適用されている、
look like this where there may
そこでは幾つかのクラスタに
not be several very
綺麗に分けられるようには
well separated clusters.
見えない。
Here is an example application, to t-shirt sizing.
これはTシャツのサイズに関する適用の例だ。
Let's say you are a t-shirt
あなたはTシャツ作ってる会社だとしよう、
manufacturer you've done is you've gone
あなたは自分たちが
to the population that you
Tシャツを売りたい、と思っている
want to sell t-shirts to, and
母集団に対して、
you've collected a number of
たくさんのサンプルの
examples of the height and weight
身長と体重の
of these people in your
データを集めた、
population and so, well I
つまり、えー、
guess height and weight tend to
たぶん身長と体重は
be positively highlighted so maybe
正の相関があるだろうから、
you end up with a data
こんな感じのデータセットに
set like this, you know, with
なるだろう。
a sample or set of
様々な人で構成されたサンプルの
examples of different peoples heights and weight.
人々の身長と体重。
Let's say you want to size your t shirts.
Tシャツのサイズを決めたいと思ってるとしよう。
Let's say I want to design
3つのサイズ、S、M、LのTシャツの
and sell t shirts of three
デザインをして売りたい、
sizes, small, medium and large.
としよう。
So how big should I make my small one?
ではその時、Sはどのくらいの大きさにすべきだろう？
How big should I my medium?
Mのサイズはどのくらいの大きさ？
And how big should I make my large t-shirts.
そしてLのTシャツは、どのくらいの大きさにすべきか？
One way to do that would
それを決める一つの方法としては、
to be to run my k means
右に示したこのデータセットに対し
clustering logarithm on this data
K-Meansクラスタリングアルゴリズムを
set that I have shown on
適用する、というのがある。
the right and maybe what
するとたぶんK-Meansが
K Means will do is group
行う事は、
all of these points into one
これら全部の点を
cluster and group all
一つのクラスタに、
of these points into a
これらの点全部を
second cluster and group
二番目のクラスタに、
all of those points into a third cluster.
そしてこれらの点全部を三番目のクラスタにグループ分けする、という事だ。
So, even though the data, you
つまり、もともとのデータセットが
know, before hand it didn't
3つの異なるクラスタに
seem like we had 3
分かれているようには見えない
well separated clusters, K Means will
のにも関わらず、K-Meansは
kind of separate out the data
複数のクラスタに
into multiple pluses for you.
分けてくれるのだ。
And what you can do is then
そこから可能な事としては、
look at this first population of
この最初の人々を
people and look at
彼らを見て、
them and, you know, look
彼らの身長と体重を見て、
at the height and weight, and
そして
try to design a small
SのTシャツをデザインする、という事。
t-shirt so that it kind
最初の
of fits this first population of
人々にうまく
people well and then design
合うように。
a medium t-shirt and design a large t-shirt.
そしてその後で、MのTシャツとLのTシャツをデザインする。
And this is in fact kind of
これはつまり、マーケットセグメンテーションの
an example of market segmentation
例となっている、
where you're using K Means to separate your
そこではK-Meansを使って、
market into 3 different segments.
マーケットを3つのセグメントに分けている。
So you can design a product
つまりこれで、S、M、Lに分けて
separately that is a small, medium, and large t-shirts,
Tシャツをデザイン出来る、
that tries to suit
3つのサブ集団の
the needs of each of your
ニーズに
3 separate sub-populations well.
良く合うように。
So that's the K Means algorithm.
以上がK-Meansアルゴリズムです。
And by now you should
ここまでで、もうK-Meansを
know how to implement the K
どうやって実装するか、そして
Means Algorithm and kind of get it to work for some problems.
どんな問題に適用出来るかを理解したはずだ。
But in the next few videos
だが次に続くいくつかのビデオで
what I want to do is
K-Meansの要点を
really get more deeply into the nuts
より深く話していくのと
and bolts of K means and
実際にとてもうまくやる為に
to talk a bit about how to actually get this to work really well.
必要な事をちょろっと話していきたい。